Guide to the New Jewish Agenda Records TAM.183
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
New Jewish Agenda Records
circa 1980-1992
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
New Jewish Agenda (Organization)
Rawson, Tom
Stein, Harry
Polishuk, Sandy, 1940-
Oren, Michael
Balka, Christie
TAM.183
44.75 Linear Feet in 40 record cartons, 10 manuscript boxes, and 1 photograph box.
New Jewish Agenda (1980-1992), was a progressive multi-issue organization whose members included secular and observant Jews drawn from many sectors of the Left. NJA had some forty-five local chapters and five task forces: Middle East, Economic and Social Justice, Nuclear Disarmament, Central America, and the Feminism (later to include AIDS) task force. NJA also sought to develop a progressive Jewish cultural and religious ethos, reflected in its creation of The Shalom Seders: Three Haggadahs (1984). The process-oriented, "participatory democracy" political culture of NJA complicated its efforts to deal with its infiltration, circa 1987, by the New Alliance Party, whose views were antithetical to those of NJA. The organization also faced hostility from mainstream organized Jewry for its critical view of Israeli foreign policy, ongoing financial difficulties, and the erosion of some of its membership to other, usually single-issue progressive Jewish organizations, and eventually disbanded in 1992. The collection contains national administrative records, including convention, national council and steering council records, including minutes, correspondence, internal bulletins, reports, mailings, membership lists, press releases, some officers' records (for example, those of Rena Bernards and Anna Jaffe); fundraising, task force and chapter records (including extensive files on the Portland, OR chapter), issues of its national newsletters, Agenda, Agenda-in-Brief and Gesher (published by the Feminist Task Force), photographs, audio sound recording and printed ephemera produced by NJA and other progressive (especially Jewish) organizations.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by the New Jewish Agenda in 1996; additional materials were donated by the organization between 2003 and 2013 and from Christine Balka in 2003, Sandy Polishuk and Harry Stein in 2006, Tom Rawson in 2011, Michael Oren in 2013 and Amy Svirsky in 2018. The accession numbers associated with these donations are 2003.029, 2003.030 2011.001, 2011.069, 2013.034 and 2019.025.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into six series:
Missing Title
Records
Portland, Oregon Chapter Records
Linda Eber Materials
Tom Rawson Files
Photographs
Ithaca, New York Chapter Records
Materials in Series I-IV, and VI are arranged in the order in which they were received.
Historical Note
New Jewish Agenda (1980-1992), aka "Agenda," identified itself as "a Jewish voice among progressives and a progressive voice among Jews." NJA was a multi-issue organization that included secular and observant Jews, Jews from the organized Left (principally the New Left of the 1960s-1970s), and politically unaffiliated Jews; it was organized into some forty-five local chapters. The political concerns of NJA were reflected in the names of the task forces through which the bulk of its activity was conducted: the Middle East Task Force (advocating a two-state solution to the Israeli-Palestinian conflict, and opposing settlements in the occupied territories), the Economic and Social Justice Task Force, the Nuclear Disarmament Task Force, the Central America Task Force (in particular opposing U.S. policy in El Salvador and Nicaragua), and the Feminism (later to include AIDS) Task Force, which reflected the strong presence of women and homosexuals in Agenda. NJA also sought to develop a progressive Jewish cultural and religious ethos, reflected in its creation of The Shalom Seders: Three Haggadahs (1984), and also devoted some attention to the issues of Soviet Jewry and Ethiopian Jews. The process-oriented, "participatory democracy" political culture of NJA complicated its efforts to deal with its infiltration, circa 1987, by the New Alliance Party, a political cult whose views were antithetical to those of NJA. The organization also faced hostility from mainstream organized Jewry for its critical view of Israeli foreign policy, ongoing financial difficulties, and the erosion of some of its membership to other, usually single-issue progressive Jewish organizations, and eventually disbanded in 1992.
New Jewish Agenda (1980-1992), aka "Agenda," identified itself as "a Jewish voice among progressives and a progressive voice among Jews." NJA was a multi-issue organization that included secular and observant Jews, Jews from the organized Left (principally the New Left of the 1960s-1970s), and politically unaffiliated Jews; it was organized into some forty-five local chapters. The political concerns of NJA were reflected in the names of the task forces through which the bulk of its activity was conducted: the Middle East Task Force (advocating a two-state solution to the Israeli-Palestinian conflict, and opposing settlements in the occupied territories), the Economic and Social Justice Task Force, the Nuclear Disarmament Task Force, the Central America Task Force (in particular opposing U.S. policy in El Salvador and Nicaragua), and the Feminism (later to include AIDS) Task Force, which reflected the strong presence of women and homosexuals in Agenda. NJA also sought to develop a progressive Jewish cultural and religious ethos, reflected in its creation of The Shalom Seders: Three Haggadahs (1984), and also devoted some attention to the issues of Soviet Jewry and Ethiopian Jews. The process-oriented, "participatory democracy" political culture of NJA complicated its efforts to deal with its infiltration, circa 1987, by the New Alliance Party, a political cult whose views were antithetical to those of NJA. The organization also faced hostility from mainstream organized Jewry for its critical view of Israeli foreign policy, ongoing financial difficulties, and the erosion of some of its membership to other, usually single-issue progressive Jewish organizations, and eventually disbanded in 1992.
Sources
Block, Ethan D. "One Voice Less for the Jewish Left: New Jewish Agenda, 1981-1993."http://www.newjewishagenda.net/PDFs/onelessvoice.pdf)
Nepon, Emily. "New Jewish Agenda: The History of an Organization, 1980-1992." Senior thesis, Goddard College, 2006, and related material (http://www.newjewishagenda.net/).
"New Jewish Agenda." Wikipedia (http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New_Jewish_Agenda). (March 2009)
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Americans for Progressive Israel Records (TAM 147)
Scope and Contents
The collection contains national administrative records, including convention, national council and steering council records, including minutes, correspondence, internal bulletins, reports, mailings, membership lists, press releases, some officer's records ( including those of Rena Bernards and Anna Jaffe); fundraising, task force and chapter records (including extensive files on the Portland, OR and Ithaca, NY chapters), issues of its national periodicals Agenda, Agenda-in-Brief, Internal Discussion Bulletin, Internal Discussion Bulletin on Anti-Semitism, and Gesher (published by the Feminist Task Force), printed ephemera produced by NJA and other progressive (especially Jewish) organizations, photographs, one audio sound recording, cassette, one box of files of Linda Eber (NJA National Program Coordinator, 1988-1992), and two boxes of Tom Rawson Files (Boston Chapter, miscellaneous national NJA files).
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Researchers interested in using audiovisual materials in this collection (films, cassette tapes, VHS tapes, et cetera) must use a digitized copy, which we refer to as an access copy. Researchers may view an item's original container, but the media themselves are not available for playback because of preservation concerns. Materials that already have already been digitized are noted in the collection's finding aid and can be requested in our reading room; materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. These requests are free of charge and can be made in anticipation of your visit. The process typically takes four to six weeks. To request an access copy be made, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A librarian will respond to you with further information.
Clippings (information artifacts); Human rights -- West Bank.; Minutes (administrative records); Central America -- Politics and government -- 1979-; Antisemitism -- Soviet Union -- Foreign public opinion, American.; Antisemitism -- United States; Arab-Israeli conflict -- Foreign public opinion, American.; Jews -- Soviet Union -- Political and social conditions.; Jews -- United States -- Attitudes toward Israel.; Jews -- United States -- Political activity.; Jews -- United States -- Societies, etc.; Circular letters.; Social justice -- United States.; Jewish radicals -- United States.; Conferences.; Peace movements -- United States.; United States -- Foreign Relations -- Israel; Correspondence.; Human rights -- Central America; New Jewish Agenda (Organization). Middle East Task Force; New Jewish Agenda (Organization). Feminist Task Force; New Jewish Agenda (Organization). Economic and Social Justice Task Force; New Alliance Party (U.S.); New Jewish Agenda (Organization). Central America Task Force; Jaffe, Annette.; Bernards, Rena.; Eber, Linda; Polishuk, Sandy, 1940-; New Jewish Agenda (Organization); Rawson, Tom; Stein, Harry; Polishuk, Sandy, 1940-; Oren, Michael; Balka, Christie
- Series I: Records
  Arrangement
  Box "TITLES" in quotation marks are from the trans-files in which the records were originally housed.
  - National Committee and Steering Committee minutes, meetings and mailings, 1980s (Box 1)
  - National Committee and Steering Committee minutes, meetings and mailings, beginning 1987, 1987-circa 1991 (Box 2)
  - National Committee and Steering Committee minutes, meetings and mailings, 1987-89; three folders from 1982, 1982, 1987-1989 (Box 3)
  - "NJA 1987-90": Conventions, membership survey 1990; New Alliance Party; other administrative, activities, and topical files., undated, 1987-1990 (Box 4)
  - "NJA 1987-90" - National Committee and Steering Committee minutes, strategic direction meetings; Chapter Files, Providence, RI - Z, and Canada, 1987-1990 (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous: much loose material, and unlabelled files, undated, 1980s (Box 6)
  - "File cabinet drawers 1-2, 1981-82": Council meetings, correspondence, membership development, "Conference" [possibly] founding conference; topical files, 1981-1982 (Box 7)
  - "File cabinet drawers 1-2, 1981-82" conclusion: includes Steering Committee 1982-83; Internal Discussion Bulletin on Anti-Semitism, "Awareness and Action, A Resource Book on Anti-Semitism," "NJA 1985-86" [11"]: mailings, workshops, funding proposals, 1985 convention, 1981-circa 1986 (Box 8)
  - "NJA 1985-86" conclusion [11"]: National Committee correspondence, fundraising, task forces [Middle East, economic justice], 1985 convention; "Staff files, pre 1991": foundations [mostly reference material, forms, and some correspondence], contributions, thank you letters, 1985-circa 1990 (Box 9)
  - "Pre 1991 staff files": foundations [mostly reference material, forms, and some correspondence], contributions, thank you letters, circa 1982-1990 (Box 10)
  - "Pre 1991 staff files" [9"] - foundations, chapter handbook; "NJA 1980" [6"] - topical and administrative files [1980s] (Box 11)
  - "NJA 1980": Founding convention, December, 1980; Early newsletters; "Annette Jaffe's files" [11"]: Steering Committee, Task Forces, packets for events, undated, 1980 (Box 12)
  - Financial; Serials [Newsletter, Agenda, Agenda-in-Brief] Conference and convention bulletins and brochures, including some draft versions and associated reference material, 1980 (Box 13)
  - Serials, conclusion; "NJA 1983-84": begins with "Direct mail proposal" folder, also includes elections, financial, G2 merger, fundraising, 1980 (Box 14)
  - "NJA 1983-84 conclusion"; Middle East Task Force, Central America; General correspondence, National Committee, Development, Fat file of chapter flyers, newsletters, etc., 1989, 1980s (Box 15)
  - Miscellaneous staff files, 1989-90 [11"]; National Committee meetings, mailings, minutes; National convention; New Alliance Party, undated, 1989-1990 (Box 16)
  - Miscellaneous office files, including chapter activity handbook, Shalom Seders, Bay Area Arbitration, 1984 [Bay Area Chapter charter revoked for advocating aid cutoff to Israel, while national NJA policy was neutrality on this issue], undated, 1980s (Box 17)
  - Miscellaneous office files; "Miscellaneous staff files, 1980s": including the Advisory Board, 1988 report, "General Support Proposal," 1989; Middle East Task Force, Thank you letters, A-K; Large donors, undated, 1980s (Box 18)
  - Thank you letters, L-Z, General Support Proposal, other files [11"]; Middle East files, including 1983 Israel tour, undated, 1980s (Box 19)
  - Membership, circa 1988, by Chapter (Box 20)
  - Middle East files: tours, 1986-87, settlement freeze, 1987 World Zionist Congress, Americans for a Progressive Israel; Middle East Task Force, 1980s (Box 21)
  - Middle East Task Force: mailings, press releases, Internal Discussion Bulletin, 1987-90; Some 1991 documents, 1980s-1991 (Box 22)
  - Middle East: Gulf War 1991; Middle East Task Force 1982 - 1989, 1982-1991 (Box 23)
  - Middle East / Middle East Task Force, circa 1983-88, including Middle East Task Force internal documents, 1983-84; Shalom network, circa 1983-1988 (Box 24)
  - Chapter files - Akron – L, undated, 1980s (Box 25)
  - Chapter files [9"]: M - Portland, OR; Holiday services by NJA and others, undated, 1980s (Box 26)
  - Press Clips [mentioning NJA], 1980s-circa 1991 (Box 27)
  - Central America Task Force, undated, 1980s (Box 28, Box 48, 49, Box 50)
  - Central America Task Force [10"]: correspondence, Nicaragua, sanctuary; Steering Committee; "NJA History" [begins with "Lease" file]; Miscellaneous administrative, activities, and topical files, circa 1984-88, undated, 1980s (Box 29, Box 45, Box 46, Box 47)
  - "NJA History" [10"]: "E" alphabetical file, including NJA elections, Economic justice, El Salvador; Miscellaneous 1985 files; "Rena Bernards' files," [begins with "negative mail" folder, and includes "Platform," 1982], undated, 1980s (Box 30)
  - "Miscellaneous 1985 [Rena] Bernards' files": alphabetical by keyword, M – Z: contains administrative, activities, and topical files, including National Committee, Nairobi, nuclear weapons, and volunteers (Box 31)
  - Middle East, A - N [roughly alphabetical by keyword]: administrative, activities, and topical files, Undated, 1980s-circa 1992 (Box 32)
  - Middle East [8"] N - Z [alphabetical by keyword]; Disarmament / Soviet Jewry / Economic and Social Justice Task Force, [most material is ESJTF and Disarmament, little on Soviet Jewry], undated, 1980s-circa 1992 (Box 33)
  - "Disarmament /Soviet Jewry / Economic and Social Justice Task Force," conclusion [11"]: mostly peace activity, ESJTF; Gesher [Feminist task force newsletter of NJA], Jewish Socialist, undated, 1980s-circa 1991 (Box 34)
  - Jewish Organizations, mostly progressive: printed ephemera and/or correspondence with NJA [box is half full], circa 1980-1982 (Box 35)
  - Middle East activities and Task Force, Internal Discussion Bulletin, 1982-1990 (Box 36)
- Series II: Portland, Oregon Chapter Records.
  - Portland Chapter: about half of box consists of envelopes addressed to Harry Stein; the box contains a "NJA History" envelope, chapter and national newsletters (Agenda), ephemera, including from other progressive organizations, and some correspondence, circa 1982-1990 (Box 37)
  - Portland Chapter: about half of box consists of envelopes addressed to Harry Stein; the box contains chapter and national newsletters (Agenda), ephemera, including from other progressive organizations, and some correspondence, circa 1982-1990 (Box 38)
- Series III: Linda Eber Files, circa 1988-1991
  - Linda Eber Files, circa 1988-1991 (Box 39)
    Scope and Content Note
    Contents description provided by Linda Eber (NJA National Program Coordinator, 1988-1992) follows:
    Carrying It On: National Conference Organizing Against Anti-Semitism and Racism (November 8-10, 1991, Philadelphia):
    Proceedings; Xerozes of speeches; Transcripts of taped speeches; Organizing papers including letters to panelists, workshop leaders permission forms, confirmation agreements (including Julian Bond and Grace Paley), panelist biographies; Various organizing papers, training packet; Conference booklet. Awareness and Action: A Resource Book on Anti-Semitism, 1991
    New Jewish Agenda (NJA) Chapter Handbook
    Draft Manual for Organizing National Conferences
    Resolutions and Notes, Platform
    Notebook with various task force organizing notes (1988)
    Jewish Womens' Committee To End The Occupation file (JWCEO)
    Central America Task Force Packet, 4/1989
    Discussion Bulletin on Zionism, 1986)
    Misc. organizing papers, pamphlets, bulletins, correspondence and notes
  - Audio and Videocassettes, 1991 (Box 39A)
    "Carrying It On" NJA conference, audiocassettes, 1991; Ron Young, speech, videoccassette.
- Series IV: Tom Rawson Files, circa 1980-1992
  - Boston New Jewish Agenda Chapter Records plus Miscellaneous National NJA Records (Includes Middle East Task Force), circa 1980-1992 (Box 40)
  - National New Jewish Agenda Records, Miscellaneous, circa 1980-1992 (Box 41)
- Series V: Photographs, circa 1982-1989
  This series includes 241 black and white photographs, 52 color photographs, 6 photocopies, 43 contact sheets, 3 strips of 110 film, a 2 1/4" negative, about 41 rolls of 35mm negatives, 5 4x5 negatives, a copy of the minutes from a meeting of the Steering Committee, an invitation to "The Arab and the Israeli," hate mail, and 15 graphics for an unspecified publication.
  - 1 black and white photograph, 1 color photograph, 1982 (Box 42, Folder 1)
  - Kadima Seder: 1 black and white photograph, 1 color photograph, 1984 (Box 42, Folder 2)
  - NJA Seder: 3 color photographs, 1984 (Box 42, Folder 3)
  - Sukkat Shalom: 11 black and white photographs, 4 color photographs, 1984 (Box 42, Folder 4)
  - 14 black and white photographs, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - 7 black and white photographs, 1987 (Box 42, Folder 6)
  - Palestine National Council, Algiers: 5 lack and white photographs, 2 color photographs, Apr 1987 (Box 42, Folder 7)
  - Tree Planting: 3 black and white photographs, 1987 (Box 42, Folder 8)
  - 2 black and white photographs, 1988 (Box 42, Folder 9)
  - NJA Steering Committee goes to Ratner's: 21 black and white photographs, 1988 (Box 42, Folder 10)
  - 3 black and white photographs, 1989 (Box 42, Folder 11)
  - Convention: 1 black and white photograph, 1989 (Box 42, Folder 12)
  - Convention Contacts, 1989 (Box 42, Folder 13)
  - Clippings, undated (Box 42, Folder 14)
  - Concert: 5 black and white photographs, undated (Box 42, Folder 15)
  - Contact Sheets, undated (Box 42, Folder 16)
  - Day care: 2 black and white photographs, undated (Box 42, Folder 17)
  - Demonstrations/Protests: 14 black and white photographs, 13 color photographs, undated (Box 42, Folder 18)
  - Irene Fertik, Photographer: Contact Sheet with Matching Negatives, undated (Box 42, Folder 19)
  - Irene Fertik, Photographer: Prints: 9 black and white photographs, undated (Box 42, Folder 20)
  - Irene Fertik, Photographer: Prints with Matching Negatives: 8 black and white photograhs, undated (Box 42, Folder 21)
  - Ilene Umen: Contacts with Matching Negatives, undated (Box 42, Folder 22)
  - Mobilization for Survival "Peace Presence" last Tisha B'av/Hiroshima Day at the Federal Building in Milwaukee: 1 black and white photograph, undated (Box 42, Folder 23)
  - Party: 4 color photographs, undated (Box 42, Folder 24)
  - Passport Photograph: 6 black and white photographs, undated (Box 42, Folder 25)
  - Paul Faer Photographs: 8 black and white photographs, undated (Box 42, Folder 26)
  - Photographs mounted on board: 12 black and white photographs, undated (Box 42, Folder 27)
  - Portraits: 23 black and white photographs, undated (Box 42, Folder 28)
  - Color prints with matching 110 negatives: 16 color photographs, undated (Box 42, Folder 29)
  - Prints with matching 35mm negatives: 12 black and white photographs, undated (Box 42, Folder 30)
  - Prints with matching 4x5 negatives: 2 black and white photographs, undated (Box 42, Folder 31)
  - Shabat: 1 black and white photograph, undated (Box 42, Folder 32)
  - Speakers: 7 black and white photographs, undated (Box 42, Folder 33)
  - Miscellaneous: 26 black and white photographs, 6 color photographs, undated (Box 42, Folder 34)
  - Miscellaneous other than photographs, undated (Box 42, Folder 35)
  - Unspecified Events: 29 black and white photographs, 2 color photographs, undated (Box 42, Folder 36)
  - NJA Steering Committee goes to Ratner's: 35mm negatives, 1988 (Box 43, Folder 1)
  - Convention: 35mm negatives, 1989 (Box 43, Folder 2)
  - 110 negatives with matching prints, undated (Box 43, Folder 3)
  - 35mm negatives with matching prints, undated (Box 43, Folder 4)
  - 4x5 negatives with matching prints, undated (Box 43, Folder 5)
  - Charles Feinberg: 35mm negatives, undated (Box 43, Folder 6)
  - Ilene Umen Negatives with matching contacts: 35mm negatives, undated (Box 43, Folder 7)
  - Irene Fertik, Photographer: negatives with matching contacts and some matching prints, 35mm negatives, undated (Box 43, Folder 8)
  - Leningrad Synagogue: 4x5 negatives, undated (Box 43, Folder 9)
  - Unlabeled: negatives, undated (Box 43, Folder 10)
- Series VI: Ithaca, New York Chapter Records, circa 1980-1992
  Original folder titles were maintained when given, and loose materials were assigned titles by the archivist. Pamphlets and documents that arrived loose in boxes or stored in overstuffed folders were rehoused into archival folders. Folder "TITLES" in quotation marks are from the trans-files in which the records were originally housed.
  Scope and Contents
  This box contains correspondence, newsletters, meeting minutes, related newsclippings and publications and one sound recording audio cassette.
  - "NJA - Business", 1984-1988 (Box 44, Folder 1)
  - "Survey", 1986 (Box 44, Folder 2)
  - "Holiday Info", 1982-1987 (Box 44, Folder 3-4)
  - Article, 1988 (Box 44, Folder 5)
  - "Newsletters", 1988 (Box 44, Folder 6)
  - "Passover Handouts and Songs", circa 1980s, undated (Box 44, Folder 7)
  - "Passover Haggadot", 1983-1984 (Box 44, Folder 8-9)
  - Convention Materials and Publications, 1985-1987 (Box 44, Folder 10-11)
  - Chapter Handbook, 1986 (Box 44, Folder 12)
  - "National Council News and Notes", 1986-1988 (Box 44, Folder 13)
  - "Chapter Newsletters", 1986-1987 (Box 44, Folder 14)
  - Administrative Records, circa 1980s, undated (Box 44, Folder 15)
  - Articles, 1982-1987 (Box 44, Folder 16)
  - Newsletters, 1981-1987 (Box 44, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, 1986-1987 (Box 44, Folder 18)